[
    {
        "question": "Which organization collaborated with NASA's ICESat-2 to create the first undersea map of the submerged \u2018Ram Setu\u2019?",
        "options": [
            "Geological Survey of India (GSI)",
            "National Institute of Oceanography (NIO)",
            "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
            "Archaeological Survey of India (ASI)"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was India\u2019s first World Peace Centre inaugurated?",
        "options": [
            "New Delhi",
            "Mumbai",
            "Gurugram, Haryana",
            "Varanasi"
        ],
        "answer": "Gurugram, Haryana"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization established India\u2019s first World Peace Center?",
        "options": [
            "Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan",
            "Ramakrishna Mission",
            "Ahimsa Vishwa Bharti",
            "Art of Living Foundation"
        ],
        "answer": "Ahimsa Vishwa Bharti"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which former President of India attended the inauguration of the first World Peace Center?",
        "options": [
            "Pratibha Patil",
            "APJ Abdul Kalam",
            "Ram Nath Kovind",
            "K. R. Narayanan"
        ],
        "answer": "Ram Nath Kovind"
    },
    {
        "question": "What global platforms is India\u2019s first World Peace Center expected to amplify India's voice on?",
        "options": [
            "World Economic Forum and G20.",
            "United Nations (UN) and World Parliament of Religions.",
            "International Monetary Fund and World Bank.",
            "Olympics and FIFA."
        ],
        "answer": "United Nations (UN) and World Parliament of Religions."
    },
    {
        "question": "Where are the Khelo India Winter Games 2025 scheduled to be held?",
        "options": [
            "Shimla",
            "Manali",
            "Gulmarg, Jammu and Kashmir",
            "Auli"
        ],
        "answer": "Gulmarg, Jammu and Kashmir"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where is the Hockey India League 2024-25 scheduled to be held?",
        "options": [
            "Kalinga Stadium, Bhubaneswar",
            "Major Dhyan Chand National Stadium, Delhi",
            "Birsa Munda Hockey Stadium, Rourkela",
            "M. A. Chidambaram Stadium, Chennai"
        ],
        "answer": "Birsa Munda Hockey Stadium, Rourkela"
    },
    {
        "question": "On December 6, which festival, inaugurated by the Prime Minister, showcased Northeast India's arts, crafts, and traditions?",
        "options": [
            "Rashtriya Kala Utsav",
            "Bharat Shilp Mahotsav",
            "Northeast Heritage Festival",
            "Ashtalakshmi Mahotsav",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the purpose of the MoU to be signed between the National Minorities Development and Finance Corporation (NMDFC) and the Dalit Indian Chamber of Commerce and Industry (DICCI)?",
        "options": [
            "To promote digital literacy among marginalized communities",
            "To empower marginalized communities through entrepreneurship",
            "To provide financial aid for education",
            "To support healthcare initiatives for marginalized groups",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which department is developing the National Legal Metrology Portal (eMaap) to centralize legal metrology processes and enhance consumer protection?",
        "options": [
            "Department of Industrial Policy and Promotion",
            "Department of Consumer Affairs",
            "Department of Economic Affairs",
            "Department of Commerce",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was India's first bio-bitumen highway inaugurated?",
        "options": [
            "Delhi",
            "Mumbai",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Nagpur",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the portal developed by the Department of Telecommunications to empower citizens against fraud communications and unsolicited commercial communications?",
        "options": [
            "Bharat Net Portal",
            "Sanchar Saathi Portal",
            "Sanchar Suraksha Portal",
            "Tele Safeguard Portal",
            "Sanchar Safeguard Portal"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What improvement in the Sex Ratio at Birth (SRB) of the girl child in India has been recorded under the Beti Bachao Beti Padhao scheme between 2014-15 and 2023-24?",
        "options": [
            "From 920 to 940",
            "From 918 to 930",
            "From 915 to 925",
            "From 910 to 920",
            "From 905 to 925"
        ],
        "answer": "From 918 to 930"
    },
    {
        "question": "With which country is India conducting the 4th edition of the joint military exercise HARIMAU SHAKTI in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Indonesia",
            "Malaysia",
            "Thailand",
            "Vietnam",
            "Myanmar"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under which scheme has the Central Board of Direct Taxes launched the electronic campaign to address mismatches in income and transactions?",
        "options": [
            "Digital Tax Compliance Scheme, 2023",
            "Income Disclosure Initiative, 2024",
            "e-Verification Scheme, 2021",
            "Annual Information Monitoring Program",
            "Both 1 and 2"
        ],
        "answer": "e-Verification Scheme, 2021"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which state is the Adani Krishnapatnam Port, which has been granted permission to import petroleum by sea from August 28, 2024, to March 1, 2026, located?",
        "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Odisha",
            "Gujarat",
            "Andhra Pradesh",
            "Maharashtra"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which initiative was launched to promote Indian Sign Language (ISL) as a language and a subject?",
        "options": [
            "Bharat Digital Channel",
            "PM e-Vidya DTH 24\u00d77 Channel",
            "ISL Learning Network",
            "Digital Bharat Education Hub",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which state in India received a $188.28 million loan from the World Bank to boost economic growth in backward districts?",
        "options": [
            "Gujarat",
            "Maharashtra",
            "Bihar",
            "Uttar Pradesh",
            "Madhya Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Linen Inspection and Sorting Assistant (LISA) system is an initiative of which organization?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Textile",
            "Indian Railways",
            "Ministry of Civil Aviation",
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Ministry of Consumer Affairs"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Railways"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which initiative was launched by Dr. Jitendra Singh on Good Governance Day to strengthen Panchayati Raj Institutions?",
        "options": [
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Aur",
            "CPGRAMS Annual Samvelan",
            "Viksit Panchayat Karmayogi",
            "Single Simplified Pension Plan",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which occasion will the government launch the Jago Grahak Jago App and Jagriti App to enhance consumer safety?",
        "options": [
            "National Consumer Day",
            "World Consumer Rights Day",
            "National Safety Day",
            "Cyber Security Day",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "National Consumer Day"
    },
    {
        "question": "As of now ( Nov 24 ) , how many accounts have been opened under the Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana (PMJDY), and how many of them are inoperative?",
        "options": [
            "50.20 crore accounts opened, 12.50 crore inoperative",
            "54.03 crore accounts opened, 11.30 crore inoperative",
            "53.50 crore accounts opened, 10.80 crore inoperative",
            "55.00 crore accounts opened, 9.00 crore inoperative",
            "52.10 crore accounts opened, 13.00 crore inoperative"
        ],
        "answer": "54.03 crore accounts opened, 11.30 crore inoperative"
    },
    {
        "question": "Rhino reintroduction efforts have gained momentum in which wildlife sanctuary in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Namdapha National Park",
            "Dibang Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Ering Wildlife Sanctuary",
            "Mouling National Park",
            "Pakke Tiger Reserve"
        ],
        "answer": "Ering Wildlife Sanctuary"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is India\u2019s total external debt in 2023, as per the World Bank International Debt Report?",
        "options": [
            "$610.67 billion",
            "$635.84 billion",
            "$646.79 billion",
            "$655.74 billion",
            "$675.95 billion"
        ],
        "answer": "$646.79 billion"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many children received the Pradhan Mantri Rashtriya Bal Puraskar from President Murmu in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "10 children",
            "17 children",
            "20 children",
            "27 children",
            "37 children"
        ],
        "answer": "17 children"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following Central Armed Police Forces celebrated its 60th raising day in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Central Reserve Police Force",
            "Border Security Force",
            "Sashastra Seema Bal",
            "Indo-Tibetan Border Police",
            "CISF"
        ],
        "answer": "Border Security Force"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where will the 2025 Para Athletics World Championships be hosted in India?",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Delhi",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Chennai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "SheSTEM 2024, an initiative of the India-Nordic BEST project, focused on which key area for energy solutions?",
        "options": [
            "Solar Power & Wind Energy",
            "Battery Technology and Energy Storage",
            "Hydroelectric Power & Semiconductors",
            "AI in Satellite Communication System",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "Battery Technology and Energy Storage"
    },
    {
        "question": "According to the India State of Forest Report 2023, by how much has India's forest cover increased since 2021?",
        "options": [
            "1,000 sq. km",
            "1,445 sq. km",
            "2,000 sq. km",
            "800 sq. km",
            "777 sq. km"
        ],
        "answer": "1,445 sq. km"
    },
    {
        "question": "India has surpassed $1 trillion in Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) from April 2000 to September 2024. How much of this FDI has been recorded since 2014, reflecting a 119% increase over the previous decade?",
        "options": [
            "$500.2 billion",
            "$667.4 billion",
            "$805.9 billion",
            "$1 trillion",
            "$904.9 billion"
        ],
        "answer": "$667.4 billion"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Union Minister recently unveiled the Anna Chakra, designed to optimize logistics under the Public Distribution System (PDS) and the SCAN Portal, which automates subsidy claim submissions and settlements under the National Food Security Act (NFSA) for faster processing?",
        "options": [
            "Shri Rajnath Singh",
            "Shri Pralhad Joshi",
            "Shri Nitin Gadkari",
            "Shri Piyush Goyal",
            "Shri Jagdeep Dhankar"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Parliament passed the Bharatiya Vayuyan Vidheyak 2024. Which old act does the Bharatiya Vayuyan Vidheyak 2024 replace?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Aviation Act, 1920",
            "Civil Aviation Act, 1950",
            "Aeronautics Act, 1945",
            "Aircraft Act, 1934",
            "Airplane Act, 1999"
        ],
        "answer": "Aircraft Act, 1934"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of India's first indigenous macrolide antibiotic, which aims to address antimicrobial resistance (AMR)?",
        "options": [
            "Nafithromycin",
            "Amoxyclav",
            "Ciprofloxacin",
            "Doxycycline",
            "None of the Above"
        ],
        "answer": "Nafithromycin"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which researcher from the Zoological Survey of India (ZSI) is credited with discovering the new species of pangolin, named the Indo-Burmese pangolin (Manis indoburmanica), in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Lenrik Konchok",
            "Suresh Naik",
            "Ramesh Pandey",
            "Deepa Sharma",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ministry launched the 'e-student visa' and 'e-student-x visa' for foreign students on January 5, 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Education",
            "Ministry of External Affairs",
            "Ministry of Home Affairs",
            "Ministry of Human Resource Development",
            "Ministry of Skill Development and Entrepreneurship"
        ],
        "answer": "Ministry of Home Affairs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which department organized the workshop on the National Anubhav Awards Scheme, 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Department of Personnel & Training",
            "Department of Pension & Pensioners' Welfare",
            "Department of Administrative Reforms & Public Grievances",
            "Ministry of Social Justice & Empowerment",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which telecom company has launched the IFTV platform in partnership with Skypro and PlayboxTV for offering over 550 Live TV channels and premium OTT apps in India?",
        "options": [
            "Airtel",
            "BSNL",
            "Reliance Jio",
            "Vodafone Idea",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "India's first underwater metro tunnel, inaugurated in 2024, is located in which city?",
        "options": [
            "Mumbai",
            "Chennai",
            "Delhi",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Kolkata"
        ],
        "answer": "Kolkata"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the 9th Swachh Survekshan Toolkit and Super Swachh League launched by Union Minister Manohar Lal?",
        "options": [
            "Promote rural cleanliness",
            "Enhance urban cleanliness and innovation among ULBs",
            "Simplify rural sanitation programs",
            "Introduce competitions for rural community development",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Enhance urban cleanliness and innovation among ULBs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements regarding the Union Cabinet approvals on January 1, 2025 is/are correct?\n1. The Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana (PMFBY) and Restructured Weather Based Crop Insurance Scheme (RWBCIS) have been extended till 2025-26.\n2. The Union Cabinet approved the creation of a Fund for Innovation and Technology (FIAT) with an outlay of Rs. 824.77 crore.\n3. The One-time Special Package for Di-Ammonium Phosphate (DAP) will end on 1st March 2025.",
        "options": [
            "Only 1 and 2",
            "Only 2 and 3",
            "Only 1 and 3",
            "Only 1",
            "All 1, 2, and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "Only 1 and 2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who serves as the convener of the Island Development Agency (IDA), which was constituted by the Home Ministry in 2017 to promote sustainable development of the islands of India?",
        "options": [
            "Union Minister of Environment, Forest and Climate Change",
            "CEO of NITI Aayog",
            "Prime Minister of India",
            "Minister of State for Home Affairs",
            "Cabinet Secretary"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which schemes has the Union Cabinet approved the continuation of until 2025-26 with a \u20b969,515.71 crore outlay?",
        "options": [
            "Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana and Pradhan Mantri Kisan Yojana",
            "Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana and Restructured Weather Based Crop Insurance Scheme",
            "National Agricultural Market Scheme and Pradhan Mantri Kisan Samman Nidhi",
            "Pradhan Mantri Krishi Sinchayee Yojana and National Livelihood Mission",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana and Restructured Weather Based Crop Insurance Scheme"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the age bracket for women eligible for the recently launched Bima Sakhi Yojana?",
        "options": [
            "16 to 60 years",
            "21 to 65 years",
            "18 to 70 years",
            "25 to 70 years",
            "10 to 70 years"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the affordable cafe initiative launched by the Ministry of Civil Aviation at airports and managed by the Airports Authority of India?",
        "options": [
            "Aero Caf\u00e9",
            "Aviator Bistro",
            "Udaan Yatri Cafe",
            "Sky Lounge",
            "Avian Civilian"
        ],
        "answer": "Udaan Yatri Cafe"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where has the Indian Army launched its Artificial Intelligence Incubation Centre (IAAIIC)?",
        "options": [
            "Delhi",
            "Pune",
            "Bengaluru",
            "Chandigarh",
            "Chennai"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of the 4th National Conference of Chief Secretaries held in New Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "Enhancing Infrastructure for Sustainable Growth",
            "Promoting Entrepreneurship, Employment, and Skilling",
            "Strengthening Health and Education Systems",
            "Digital Transformation for National Development",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which country has secured seven key positions in the interim organizational structure of the new Asian body formed by World Boxing, including a board member role for its Boxing Federation President?",
        "options": [
            "China",
            "Japan",
            "South Korea",
            "India",
            "Laos"
        ],
        "answer": "India"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which edition of the Raising Day Parade of the BSF was celebrated in Jodhpur, Rajasthan on 8th December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "50th",
            "55th",
            "60th",
            "65th",
            "69th"
        ],
        "answer": "60th"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under which scheme did the government provide grants of \u20b950 lakh each to two start-ups focusing on sustainable and medical textiles?",
        "options": [
            "Atal Innovation Mission",
            "GREAT scheme",
            "Start-Up India Initiative",
            "Technical Textiles Grant Program",
            "MGNREGA"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the nationwide campaign that was launched during the 4th Good Governance Week on 19th December, 2024?",
        "options": [
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Baat",
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Yatra",
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Abhiyan",
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Ore",
            "Prashasan Gaon Ki Tarakki"
        ],
        "answer": "Prashasan Gaon Ki Ore"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization has partnered with boAt to mentor and support startups in the D2C and manufacturing sectors?",
        "options": [
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Department for Promotion of Industry and Internal Trade (DPIIT)",
            "Ministry of Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises (MSME)",
            "Startup India",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the 'Track and Trace Mechanism' approved by the GST Council in December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "To monitor imports and exports",
            "To monitor GST rate expansion on certain goods",
            "To simplify GST registration process and to track the GSTIN holder locations",
            "To curb tax evasion in specified commodities",
            "To impose tax at every level"
        ],
        "answer": "To curb tax evasion in specified commodities"
    },
    {
        "question": "India has set up its first diabetes biobank in Chennai. Which two organizations collaborated to set up India's first diabetes biobank?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Council of Medical Research and Madras Diabetes Research Foundation",
            "All India Institute of Medical Sciences and Tata Trusts",
            "World Health Organization and All India Institute of Medical Sciences",
            "Indian Medical Association and National Institute of Diabetes",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Council of Medical Research and Madras Diabetes Research Foundation"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the Kisan Kavach anti-pesticide bodysuit launched by Dr. Jitendra Singh?",
        "options": [
            "It is a reusable bodysuit priced at \u20b96,000.",
            "It was developed by BRIC-inStem in collaboration with Sepio Health Pvt. Ltd.",
            "The bodysuit uses advanced nanotechnology to neutralize pesticides.",
            "The bodysuit was distributed to all Indian farmers for free at the launch event.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the total outlay approved by the Ministry of Tourism for 40 projects under the Special Assistance to States/Union Territories for Capital Investment (SASCI) guidelines?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 3,100 crore",
            "Rs 3,295 crore",
            "Rs 3,560 crore",
            "Rs 2,952 crore",
            "Rs 3,750 crore"
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 3,295 crore"
    },
    {
        "question": "How many Sewer and Septic Tank Workers (SSWs) have been identified under the NAMASTE scheme by December 2024?",
        "options": [
            "57758",
            "13604",
            "24574",
            "41800",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "57758"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ship, under the \"Navika Sagar Parikrama II\" mission, crossed Point Nemo?",
        "options": [
            "INS Rajput",
            "INS Vikramaditya",
            "INS Arihant",
            "INS Tarini",
            "INS Kolkata"
        ],
        "answer": "INS Tarini"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the SuperApp launched by Indian Railways for seamless travel?",
        "options": [
            "RailServe",
            "SwaRail",
            "RailBuddy",
            "RailConnect",
            "TravelEasy"
        ],
        "answer": "SwaRail"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the international alliance launched by India for conserving 7 big cats?",
        "options": [
            "Panthera Alliance",
            "Big Cats Global",
            "Global Tiger Trust",
            "WildCat Conservation",
            "Big Cat Alliance"
        ],
        "answer": "Big Cat Alliance"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where has India\u2019s first White Tiger Breeding Centre been approved?",
        "options": [
            "Tamil Nadu",
            "Karnataka",
            "Rajasthan",
            "Madhya Pradesh",
            "Uttar Pradesh"
        ],
        "answer": "Madhya Pradesh"
    },
    {
        "question": "What milestone has India achieved in solar energy capacity?",
        "options": [
            "100 MW",
            "50 GW",
            "100 GW",
            "20 GW",
            "150 GW"
        ],
        "answer": "100 GW"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where is the 1st BIMSTEC Youth Summit being held?",
        "options": [
            "Dhaka",
            "Gandhinagar",
            "New Delhi",
            "Colombo",
            "Kathmandu"
        ],
        "answer": "Gandhinagar"
    },
    {
        "question": "What event is being held to celebrate the 75th anniversary of the National Sample Survey (NSS)?",
        "options": [
            "NSS Special Lecture",
            "National Inaugural Event",
            "NSS Anniversary Ceremony",
            "75th NSS Conference",
            "National Economic Forum"
        ],
        "answer": "National Inaugural Event"
    },
    {
        "question": "What extension was approved by the Cabinet regarding the National Commission for Safai Karamcharis?",
        "options": [
            "One year beyond 31.03.2025",
            "Three years beyond 31.03.2025",
            "Two years beyond 31.03.2025",
            "Five years beyond 31.03.2025",
            "Extension till 2025"
        ],
        "answer": "Three years beyond 31.03.2025"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the 'Pujari Granthi Samman' scheme launched?",
        "options": [
            "New Delhi",
            "Mumbai",
            "Kolkata",
            "Chennai",
            "Varanasi"
        ],
        "answer": "New Delhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary focus of Grameen Bharat Mahotsav 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Urban development",
            "Rural empowerment",
            "Industrial growth",
            "Technological innovation",
            "Education"
        ],
        "answer": "Rural empowerment"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who addressed the inaugural session of the India Energy Week 2025?",
        "options": [
            "President Ram Nath Kovind",
            "Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman",
            "Prime Minister Narendra Modi",
            "Energy Minister Raj Kumar Singh",
            "Home Minister Amit Shah"
        ],
        "answer": "Prime Minister Narendra Modi"
    },
    {
        "question": "When will the 3rd Kashi Tamil Sangamam take place?",
        "options": [
            "January 2025",
            "February 15, 2025",
            "March 2025",
            "December 2024",
            "April 2025"
        ],
        "answer": "February 15, 2025"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the revised amount for the fixed deposit under the Dulari Kanya Scheme for institutional births of girl children in Arunachal Pradesh?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 10,000",
            "Rs 20,000",
            "Rs 25,000",
            "Rs 30,000",
            "Rs 50,000"
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 30,000"
    },
    {
        "question": "What was the previous amount of the fixed deposit for institutional births under the Dulari Kanya Scheme before it was raised?",
        "options": [
            "Rs 5,000",
            "Rs 10,000",
            "Rs 15,000",
            "Rs 20,000",
            "Rs 25,000"
        ],
        "answer": "Rs 20,000"
    },
    {
        "question": "India\u2019s first zoo-based wildlife biobank is established in which zoo?",
        "options": [
            "Nandankanan Zoological Park",
            "Padmaja Naidu Himalayan Zoological Park",
            "Nehru Zoological Park",
            "Kanha National Park",
            "Sikkim Himalayan Zoological Park"
        ],
        "answer": "Padmaja Naidu Himalayan Zoological Park"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ministry co-hosted the 9th edition of the Asia Economic Dialogue (AED) 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Finance",
            "Ministry of External Affairs",
            "Ministry of Commerce and Industry",
            "Ministry of Agriculture",
            "Ministry of Science and Technology"
        ],
        "answer": "Ministry of External Affairs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which conference was held in Udaipur with the theme \"India@2047 \u2013 A Water Secure Nation\"?",
        "options": [
            "1st National Water Conference",
            "2nd State Water Ministers' Conference",
            "River Rejuvenation Conference",
            "Climate Change Summit",
            "Water Security Forum"
        ],
        "answer": "2nd State Water Ministers' Conference"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company partnered with ASI to restore and protect historic water bodies in India?",
        "options": [
            "Tata Consultancy Services",
            "Bisleri International",
            "Coca-Cola",
            "PepsiCo",
            "Hindustan Unilever"
        ],
        "answer": "Bisleri International"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the recently launched scheme designed to enhance agricultural productivity, promote crop diversification, and strengthen post-harvest storage at panchayat and block levels?",
        "options": [
            "PM Kisan Samman Nidhi Yojana",
            "PM Krishi Vikas Yojana",
            "PM Fasal Bima Yojana",
            "PM Dhan Dhanya Krishi Yojana",
            "PM SVANIDHI"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the National Institute of Electronics and Information Technology (NIELIT) Centre of Excellence in Chip Design inaugurated which is aimed to bolster India's VLSI & semiconductor capabilities?",
        "options": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Hyderabad",
            "Noida",
            "Chennai",
            "Mumbai"
        ],
        "answer": "Noida"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recently government has said 864 km of India-Bangladesh border yet to be fenced in loksabha, Which force is responsible for guarding the India-Bangladesh border?",
        "options": [
            "Assam Rifles",
            "Border Security Force (BSF)",
            "Indo-Tibetan Border Police (ITBP)",
            "National Security Guard (NSG)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Recently, Digi Yatra app user base has crossed 10 million+ with 30,000 daily downloads. The app was launched in which year?",
        "options": [
            "2014",
            "2022",
            "2021",
            "2023",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2022"
    },
    {
        "question": "On which date was the PM Internship Scheme launched?",
        "options": [
            "September 15, 2024",
            "October 3, 2024",
            "November 10, 2024",
            "January 9, 2025",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "How much funding has been allocated for the Samudrayaan Mission in the Union Budget?",
        "options": [
            "400 crore",
            "500 crore",
            "600 crore",
            "750 crore",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "600 crore"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following groups of sites were newly added as Ramsar sites in India, bringing the total to 89?",
        "options": [
            "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "Harike Wetland (Punjab), Chilika Lake (Odisha), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "Chilika Lake (Odisha), Loktak Lake (Manipur), and Sambhar Salt Lake (Rajasthan)",
            "Only Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim) and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Sakkarakottai and Therthangal Bird Sanctuaries (Tamil Nadu), Khecheopalri Wetland (Sikkim), and Udhwa Lake (Jharkhand)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which institution has the Supreme Court appointed to prepare a plan for improving Delhi's green cover?",
        "options": [
            "Forest Research Institute (FRI)",
            "Indian Institute of Forest Management",
            "National Environmental Engineering Research Institute",
            "Central Pollution Control Board",
            "NGT"
        ],
        "answer": "Forest Research Institute (FRI)"
    },
    {
        "question": "At which port did India's Matsya-6000 submersible successfully complete its wet tests, moving closer to the 500m shallow-water trials by 2025 as part of the Samudrayan Project under the Deep Ocean Mission?",
        "options": [
            "Chennai Port",
            "Visakhapatnam Port",
            "Mumbai Port",
            "Kattupalli Port",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of the first-ever Regional Dialogue on the Global Coalition for Social Justice, scheduled for February 24-25, 2025, in New Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "\"Sustainable Development through Green Business\"",
            "\"Innovation for Social Justice and Equality\"",
            "\"Empowering Communities for Global Progress\"",
            "\"Responsible Businesses for Inclusive & Sustainable Societies\"",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "\"Responsible Businesses for Inclusive & Sustainable Societies\""
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was India's first vertical bifacial solar plant inaugurated by the Union Minister for Housing and Urban Affairs and Power Manohar Lal?",
        "options": [
            "Chennai",
            "Mumbai",
            "New Delhi",
            "Bengaluru",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which scheme has been extended to 2025-26 with the provision of 100% pulse procurement for the next four years?",
        "options": [
            "PM-KISAN",
            "PM-AASHA",
            "Fasal Bima Yojana",
            "National Food Security Scheme",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "PM-AASHA"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which ministry is organizing the Aadi Mahotsav 2025, from February 16 to 24, 2025, at Major Dhyan Chand National Stadium, New Delhi?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Tribal Affairs",
            "Ministry of Culture",
            "Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment",
            "Ministry of Rural Development",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Ministry of Tribal Affairs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organizations launched the 'AI for Entrepreneurship' initiative to train 1 lakh youth?",
        "options": [
            "MSDE, NSDC, and Intel India",
            "AICTE, Ministry of Education, and Google",
            "NITI Aayog, ISRO, and Intel India",
            "Ministry of Electronics and IT, IBM, and NSDC",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "MSDE, NSDC, and Intel India"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the maximum health insurance coverage provided under the Ayushman Bharat Vay Vandana Scheme for senior citizens?",
        "options": [
            "\u20b95 lakh per year",
            "\u20b910 lakh per year",
            "\u20b92 lakh per year",
            "\u20b93 lakh per year",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization launched the J. C. Bose Grant (JBG) to support senior Indian scientists and engineers in advancing research?",
        "options": [
            "Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR)",
            "Anusandhan National Research Foundation (ANRF)",
            "Department of Science and Technology (DST)",
            "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Anusandhan National Research Foundation (ANRF)"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the full form of the NAKSHA program that aims to create and update land records in urban areas?",
        "options": [
            "National Agricultural Knowledge-based Survey of Habitations",
            "National Automated Knowledge Survey for Housing Applications",
            "National Aerial Knowledge-based Survey for Housing Authorities",
            "National Geospatial Knowledge-based Land Survey of Urban Habitations",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "National Geospatial Knowledge-based Land Survey of Urban Habitations"
    },
    {
        "question": "Union Government released XV Finance Commission Grants for Rural Local Bodies (RLBs) of Bihar, Haryana, and Sikkim for FY 2024-25. Find how many of them are rightly matched?\n1. Bihar - \u20b9869.74 crore\n2. Haryana - \u20b9210.07 crore\n3. Sikkim - \u20b96.26 crore",
        "options": [
            "Only 1 and 2 are correct",
            "Only 2 and 3 are correct",
            "All are correct",
            "Only 1 and 3 are correct",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All are correct"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which power station won the 1st prize for official language implementation at the Regional Official Language Conference in Jaipur?",
        "options": [
            "Bhakra Nangal Power Station",
            "Salal Power Station",
            "Tehri Power Station",
            "Sardar Sarovar Power Station",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Salal Power Station"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Open Network for Digital Commerce (ONDC) initiative was incorporated as a non-profit, Section-8 company and incubated at the ______.",
        "options": [
            "NITI Aayog",
            "Quality Council of India",
            "Reserve Bank of India",
            "Ministry of Commerce and Industry",
            "National Informatics Centre"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the key objective of the Aircraft Leasing Bill approved by the Indian government in 2024?",
        "options": [
            "To introduce new airlines in India, thereby making the airline market more competitive",
            "To build new aircraft manufacturing facilities in India via international collaboration",
            "To increase regressive tax benefits for airline operators.",
            "To reduce airfares by lowering leasing and financing costs for airlines.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "To reduce airfares by lowering leasing and financing costs for airlines."
    },
    {
        "question": "Who will be the Chief Guest at India's 76th Republic Day celebrations in 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Australian Prime Minister",
            "Indonesian President",
            "Canadian Prime Minister",
            "UK Prime Minister",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "The newly inaugurated Sonamarg Tunnel by PM Modi ensures all-weather road connectivity between which two locations in Jammu and Kashmir?",
        "options": [
            "Gagangeer and Sonamarg",
            "Srinagar and Leh",
            "Sonamarg and Kargil",
            "Jammu and Sonamarg",
            "Srinagar and Sonamarg"
        ],
        "answer": "Gagangeer and Sonamarg"
    },
    {
        "question": "Who launched Phase 4 of the National Educational Alliance for Technology (NEAT 4.0) in January 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Education",
            "University Grants Commission (UGC)",
            "All India Council for Technical Education (AICTE)",
            "National Board of Accreditation (NBA)",
            "National Testing Agency (NTA)"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "At which forum did Piyush Goyal launch the 'Bharat Cleantech Manufacturing Platform,' aimed at boosting solar, wind, hydrogen, and battery sectors, and positioning India as a global leader in clean energy manufacturing?",
        "options": [
            "Bharat Sustainability Summit",
            "Bharat Climate Forum 2025",
            "India Renewable Energy Forum",
            "Global Green Energy Summit",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which report stated that India's poverty rate fell below 5% in 2024, with rural poverty at 4.86% and urban poverty at 4.09%?",
        "options": [
            "RBI Report",
            "NITI Aayog Report",
            "SBI Report",
            "Ministry of Finance Report",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "SBI Report"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under which scheme has the Rural Development Ministry approved 56 watershed development projects worth \u20b9700 crore, covering approximately 2.8 lakh hectares across 10 states?",
        "options": [
            "MGNREGA",
            "National Water Mission",
            "Soil Health Management Scheme",
            "PMKSY-WDC 2.0",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the foundation stone for the new Central Ayurveda Research Institute building laid by PM Modi?",
        "options": [
            "Bengaluru",
            "Mumbai",
            "New Delhi",
            "Hyderabad",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "New Delhi"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was the closing event of the \"Hamara Samvidhan Hamara Swabhiman\" campaign organized?",
        "options": [
            "Haridwar",
            "Nashik",
            "Prayagraj",
            "Rishikesh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "In September 2024, India surpassed which milestone in renewable energy capacity?",
        "options": [
            "100 GW",
            "150 GW",
            "200 GW",
            "250 GW",
            "300 GW"
        ],
        "answer": "200 GW"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which app was launched by Union Minister Jyotiraditya Scindia to enhance telecom security and accessibility for citizens?",
        "options": [
            "National Broadband App 2.0",
            "Sanchar Saathi Mobile App",
            "Intra Circle Roaming App",
            "DBN-Connectivity App",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Sanchar Saathi Mobile App"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the Indian Army's Motorcycle Rider Display Team that set a new world record with a 20.4-foot-high human pyramid comprising 40 men on 7 motorcycles, traveling 2 kilometers along Kartavya Path?",
        "options": [
            "Bravehearts",
            "Avengers",
            "Daredevils",
            "Thunderbolts",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Daredevils"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which edition of National Voters' Day was observed on January 25?",
        "options": [
            "15th",
            "16th",
            "18th",
            "20th",
            "21st"
        ],
        "answer": "15th"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the name of the newly launched platform for managing business and organizational documents?",
        "options": [
            "DigiLocker Pro",
            "Entity Locker",
            "BizLocker",
            "Bharatiya Tijori",
            "IndiaSafe"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is true about veteran nuclear scientist Rajagopala Chidambaram, who recently passed away?",
        "options": [
            "He played a pivotal role in India's nuclear tests in 1975 and 1998.",
            "He served as the Director-General of ISRO.",
            "He passed away at AIIMS Hospital in New Delhi.",
            "He was associated with the development of India's first geo-stationary satellite.",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "He played a pivotal role in India's nuclear tests in 1975 and 1998."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two organizations partnered to foster innovation and strengthen the startup ecosystem in India?",
        "options": [
            "NITI Aayog and Startup India",
            "DPIIT and Startup Policy Forum (SPF)",
            "Ministry of Commerce and Industry and FICCI",
            "Ministry of Finance and SIDBI",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "DPIIT and Startup Policy Forum (SPF)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following warships is NOT part of the Indian Navy's Republic Day parade tableau?",
        "options": [
            "INS Surat",
            "INS Vagsheer",
            "INS Nilgiri",
            "INS Vikrant",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "question": "By which year is India aiming to end tuberculosis (TB) under the national TB control initiatives?",
        "options": [
            "2023",
            "2025",
            "2021",
            "2024",
            "2030"
        ],
        "answer": "2025"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization is conducting the National Science Drama Festival 2024-25?",
        "options": [
            "National Science Council of Museums",
            "Ministry of Science and Technology",
            "National Institute of Technology Pune",
            "Niti Aayog",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "National Science Council of Museums"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which platform is providing multilingual access in 11 languages at Mahakumbh Prayagraj 2025?",
        "options": [
            "DigiLocker",
            "UMANG App",
            "Bhashini",
            "Aarogya Setu",
            "Kumbham"
        ],
        "answer": "Bhashini"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which two Indian cities were recently added to the Global Wetland Cities list for integrating wetland preservation into their urban plans?",
        "options": [
            "Kolkata and Ahmedabad",
            "Indore and Udaipur",
            "Jaipur and Bhopal",
            "Chandigarh and Hyderabad",
            "None of the abocve"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which authority is responsible for registering Local Cable Operators (LCOs) under the amended Cable Television Network Rules, 1994?",
        "options": [
            "Ministry of Communications (MoC)",
            "Department of Telecommunication (DoT)",
            "Ministry of Information and Broadcasting (MIB)",
            "Ministry of Electronics and Information Technology (MeitY)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Ministry of Information and Broadcasting (MIB)"
    },
    {
        "question": "After the creation of two new Reserve Battalions, what will be the total number of CISF battalions?",
        "options": [
            "13",
            "15",
            "18",
            "20",
            "27"
        ],
        "answer": "15"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which company introduced a dedicated Post-Retirement Benefit (PRB) Cell to streamline post-retirement services for its employees?",
        "options": [
            "South Eastern Coalfields Limited (SECL)",
            "Coal India Limited",
            "NTPC Limited",
            "Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited (BHEL)",
            "ONGC"
        ],
        "answer": "South Eastern Coalfields Limited (SECL)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization expanded its fellowships to include non-scientists in its 2025 Fellow list?",
        "options": [
            "Indian National Science Academy (INSA)",
            "Indian Science Congress Association (ISCA)",
            "Indian Academy of Sciences (IAS)",
            "Council of Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian National Science Academy (INSA)"
    },
    {
        "question": "When will the first Lokpal Day be celebrated?",
        "options": [
            "14th January 2025",
            "15th January 2025",
            "16th January 2025",
            "17th January 2025",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Cabinet approved setting up the 8th Pay Commission to revise the salaries of central government employees and pensioners. How many employees and pensioners will be affected by it?",
        "options": [
            "49 lakh employees and 65 lakh pensioners",
            "50 lakh employees and 71 lakh pensioners",
            "45 lakh employees and 60 lakh pensioners",
            "66 lakh employees and 55 lakh pensioners",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Department of Administrative Reforms and Public Grievances has released the scheme guidelines for the National e-Governance Awards 2025. The Awards will consist of a Trophy, Certificate, and an incentive of Rs. ______ for Gold Awardees and Rs. ______ for Silver Awardees.",
        "options": [
            "5 lakhs, 3 lakhs",
            "10 lakhs, 7 lakhs",
            "15 lakhs, 10 lakhs",
            "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs",
            "7 lakhs, 3 lakhs"
        ],
        "answer": "10 lakhs, 5 lakhs"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the initiative launched to empower elected women representatives from Panchayati Raj institutions:",
        "options": [
            "Training Women Leaders Program",
            "Empowering Women in Governance",
            "Women Empowerment in Panchayats",
            "Panchayat Se Parliament",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Panchayat Se Parliament"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Faral Sakhi Initiative, launched by the Mira Bhayandar Municipal Corporation in collaboration with the Women Entrepreneurship Platform (WEP) of NITI Aayog, aims to empower women entrepreneurs by providing training and support for which of the following activities?",
        "options": [
            "Tailoring and garment manufacturing",
            "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks",
            "Handicrafts and artisanal products",
            "Organic farming and agriculture",
            "Beauty and wellness services"
        ],
        "answer": "Production and sale of traditional festive snacks"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization has given preliminary consent to sponsor the 38th National Games being hosted by Uttarakhand?",
        "options": [
            "Oil and Natural Gas Corporation (ONGC)",
            "Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited (HPCL)",
            "Bharat Petroleum Corporation Limited (BPCL)",
            "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)",
            "BHEL"
        ],
        "answer": "Indian Oil Corporation (IOC)"
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the India's OTT aggregator with which has BSNL partnered and launched IFTV Pilot in order to bolster inclusive digital connectivity and entertainment for every Indian in UP East?",
        "options": [
            "Zee5",
            "SonyLIV",
            "Hotstar",
            "OTTplay",
            "JioCinema"
        ],
        "answer": "OTTplay"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary goal of the Indian Sustainable Natural Rubber (iSNR) initiative?",
        "options": [
            "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production",
            "To increase the yield of rubber trees",
            "To focus on enhancing rubber product exports",
            "To reduce the cost of rubber production via supply-chain management",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "To prevent deforestation and support sustainable rubber production"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which initiative was launched by Shri Jayant Chaudhary to empower underserved communities through skill development?",
        "options": [
            "Vocational Training Workshops",
            "Solar-Powered Skill Vans",
            "Digital Education Hubs",
            "Green Energy Skill Program",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Solar-Powered Skill Vans"
    },
    {
        "question": "From which age bracket did the NFHS 4 data reveal about 5% of women undergoing hysterectomy?",
        "options": [
            "15-24 years",
            "25-49 years",
            "50-60 years",
            "Above 60 years",
            "75-90 years"
        ],
        "answer": "25-49 years"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the theme of the Grameen Bharat Mahotsav 2025?",
        "options": [
            "Empowering Villages through Technology",
            "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047",
            "Economic Transformation through Cooperatives",
            "Sustainable Agriculture for Rural Development",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Building a Resilient Rural India for a Viksit Bharat 2047"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which organization received Foreign Contribution Regulation Act (FCRA) approval from the Union Ministry of Home Affairs for receiving foreign funds?",
        "options": [
            "Central Tibetan Administration",
            "Tibetan Youth Congress",
            "Tibetan Government-in-Exile",
            "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "His Holiness the Dalai Lama Charitable Trust"
    },
    {
        "question": "By which year does India aim to achieve 500 gigawatts of non-fossil fuel-based energy capacity?",
        "options": [
            "2025",
            "2030",
            "2026",
            "2028",
            "2035"
        ],
        "answer": "2030"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the primary objective of the recently launched 'PLI Scheme 1.1' for the steel industry?",
        "options": [
            "Promoting export-oriented steel production",
            "Boosting small-scale steel industries in rural areas",
            "Establishing new research centers for advanced metallurgy",
            "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Enhancing steel production through Production Linked Incentives"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the total expenditure approved by the Union Cabinet for the establishment of the Third Launch Pad (TLP) at ISRO's Satish Dhawan Space Centre, and within how many months is the project expected to be completed?",
        "options": [
            "\u20b93984 crore; 36 months",
            "\u20b93984 crore; 48 months",
            "\u20b94450 crore; 48 months",
            "\u20b93984 crore; 60 months",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Under the National Health Mission (NHM) from 2021 to 2024, how many additional healthcare workers were employed?",
        "options": [
            "8 lakh",
            "10 lakh",
            "12 lakh",
            "15 lakh",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    }
]